Mss.Rec.84 Mss.Rec.84
American Philosophical Society
Mandan-Hidatsa cultural change and language studies, Fort Berthold Reservation
1967-1972
Mss.Rec.84
American Philosophical Society
11.0 Reel(s)
Includes texts, vocabulary, etc.; letter to Whitfield J. Bell, Jr.; table of contents.
11 sound tape reels (87 hr., 26 min.): analog, 1 7/8 ips, 4 track, mono; 7 in.
Bowers, Alfred W.
Driver, James
Hollow, Robert C.
Matthews, Washington, 1843-1905
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Alfred W. Bowers in 1972 (Acc. 1972 498r). This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Sacagawea; Creation--Mythology; Hidatsa Indians; Hidatsa Indians--Folklore; Hidatsa Indians--Funeral customs and rites; Hidatsa language; Hidatsa language--Dictionaries; Hidatsa mythology; Lewis and Clark Expedition (1804-1806); Mandan Indians; Mandan language; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "abandon" to "badger", 1971-08-11; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 01:00:00; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    Scope and Contents note
    This program begins with a description given by researcher of the methods and objectives of the planned recording sessions. From 13:32, the remainder of the program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program spans pgs. 335-339. Some of the English entries are skipped, and some items are added, primarily at the beginning of the list. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The researcher's voice is often faint throughout the program. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 71, channel 1.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Dictionaries; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "Badlands" to "bullet", 1971-08-11; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 02:04:32; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 339-347. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. There is a section from 01:26:08 - 01:27:22 of significant crackling, inconsistent levels, and intermittent signal loss. When transferred to RDAT tape, the original recording spanned the end of one tape and the beginning of the subsequent one. As a result, there is a small gap in the recording at 01:40:58. Three seconds of silence were inserted to reflect the gap of missing original material, which is of underdetermined length, though likely no more than a few seconds. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 71, channel 4.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Mandan language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "bundle" to "father-in-law", 1971-08-11; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 02:00:42; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 347-364. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 71, channel 2.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "feast" to "June", 1971-08-11; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 02:01:49; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 365-378. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 71, channel 3.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "June" to "knee", 1971-08-11; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:17; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 378-379. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. This recording session is interrupted at 13:37 by a knock on the door of the consultant's house. This is followed by a conversation in Hidatsa between the consultant and three women requesting his assistance at a funeral. The conversation continues through 19:41. The recording concludes with a discussion in English between the researcher and consultant regarding the Hidatsa conversation. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 1.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Funeral customs and rites; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Dictionaries; Mandan language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Account of a funeral in Hidatsa, 1971-08; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:47; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    The Hidatsa language is frequently referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 1.
    Hidatsa Indians--Funeral customs and rites; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Account of Crow Flies High band in Hidatsa, 1971-08; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:53; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    When transferred to RDAT tape, the original recording spanned the end of one tape and the beginning of the subsequent one. As a result, there is a small gap in the recording at 14:23. Three seconds of silence were inserted to reflect the gap of missing original material, which is of underdetermined length. At the resumption of the recording after the gap the sound begins at a slightly slower speed, but gradually normalizes. The Hidatsa language is frequently referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 1.
    Hidatsa Indians--History; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "knee" to "narrow", 1971-08; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:42:55; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 379-388. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 1.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "nasal apeture" to "potato", 1971-08; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 01:00:50; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 388-395. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 2.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "sandstone", 1971-08; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:38; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pg. 403. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The prior dictionary entries "potato bug" through "sand cherries" are not on the RDAT tape from which the digitized copies have been made. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 4.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Dictionaries; Mandan language; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "Saturday" to "tattoo", 1971-08; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 01:46:41; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 408-416. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The subsequent dictionary entries "Tattooed Face's Village" through "toad" are not on the RDAT tape from which the digitized copies have been made. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 2.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: "tobacco" to "year", 1971-08; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:24:11; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program concludes a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English entries in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) This program covers pgs. 418-427. Some of the English entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The prior dictionary entries "Tattooed Face's Village" through "toad" are not on the RDAT tape from which the digitized copies have been made. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 3.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Grammatical morphemes, pg. 429, 1971-08; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:17; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of elicitations of Hidatsa language information through use of a list of grammatical morphemes given in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. Frequent variations and additions to the list are made by the researcher. Includes occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Mandan grammatical morpheme worked from in this program is ''transitivizer." The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 72, channel 3.
    Anthropological linguistics; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Hidatsa language--Grammar; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Grammatical morphemes, pg. 430, 1971-08; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:14; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of elicitations of Hidatsa language information through use of a list of grammatical morphemes given in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. Frequent variations and additions to the list are made by the researcher. Includes some discussion of deer hunting and occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Mandan grammatical morpheme worked from in this program is "past participle." The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 1.
    Anthropological linguistics; Deer hunting; Hidatsa Indians--Social life and customs; Hidatsa language--Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Hidatsa language--Grammar; New Town (N.D.)
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Grammatical morphemes, pgs. 430-447, 1971-08; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 01:39:00; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of elicitations of Hidatsa language information through use of a list of grammatical morphemes given in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. Frequent variations and additions to the list are made by the researcher. Includes occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The program begins with a list of plant and animals names that does not appear to be directly derived as such from the Hollow dictionary. The grammatical morphemes elicitation begins at 00:04:50. The Mandan grammatical morphemes that are worked from in this program are: "collective," "dubitative," "conditional," "patient suffix," "continuative," "locative," "similitive," "times (postposition)," "instrumental case," "mild imperative," "directional," "possessive," "instrumentative," "ordinal," "reflexive," "evidential," "agentive," "instrumental prefix: by striking," "nominal suffix," "imperfective aspect," "quotative mood," "negative imperative proclitic," and "vertitive." The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 1.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Grammatical morphemes, pgs. 448-462, 1971-08; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:47:27; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of elicitations of Hidatsa language information through use of a list of grammatical morphemes given in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. Frequent variations and additions to the list are made by the researcher. Includes occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Mandan grammatical morphemes that are worked from in this program are: "middle voice," "iterative," "temporal subordination," "agentive," "third person possessor with kin terms," "third person pluralizer," "potential," "nominalizing prefix," "future," "indicative mood, man addressed," "interrogative, woman addressed," "indicative mood, woman addressed," "causal subordination," "interrogative, man addressed," "inchoative aspect," and "instrumental prefix: by pressure, motion away from body." The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 1.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Grammatical morphemes, pgs. 462-485, 1971-08; 02-08; 1.0 .mp3; 01:33:28; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of elicitations of Hidatsa language information through use of a list of grammatical morphemes given in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. Frequent variations and additions to the list are made by the researcher. Includes occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Mandan grammatical morphemes that are worked from in this program are: "mutative," "instrumental prefix: by heat or fire," "instrumental prefix: by foot," "second person subject of active verbs," "imperative mood, woman addressed," "typifier," "almost," "sequititive," "second person possessive pronoun," "second person ergative pronoun," "infinitive/conjuctive," "incredulative mood," "second and inclusive person pluralizer," "perfective aspect," "narrative past," "instrumental prefix: by hand, by motion toward the body," "inclusive pronoun," "definite article," "preterite," "iterative," "locative," "collective," "disjunctive," "alienable possession," "interrogative particle," "locative," and "imperative, man addressed." There is an intermittent, uncorrectable line hum from 01:01:29 - 01:01:42. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Grammatical morphemes, pgs. 485-492, 1971-08; 02-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:07; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of elicitations of Hidatsa language information through use of a list of grammatical morphemes given in Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. Frequent variations and additions to the list are made by the researcher. Includes occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The Mandan grammatical morphemes that are worked from in this program are: "inclusivizer," "dative case," "absolutive," "first person ergative pronoun," "first person subject pronoun," "instrumental prefix: by sharp pointed object," "nominal prefix of unknown meaning," "negative," and "first person possessive pronoun." The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Introductory matter, pgs. 15, 35-51, 1971-08; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:44; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The recording becomes scratchy from 25:56 through the end of the recording. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was copied from the collector's original tape 73, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 54-55, 1971-08; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:03; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The recording contains a minor, uncorrectable scratchy sound throughout. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was copied from the collector's original tape 73, channel 4.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 56-74, 1971-08; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 01:22:29; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James
    This program consists of a Hidatsa word list elicited by the reading of English terms and phrases from the Mandan-English section of Robert C. Hollow's Mandan dictionary. (See Related Resource.) Some of the entries are skipped. The Mandan equivalents from the dictionary are infrequently given. Includes occasional discussion of context and usage of given words, as well as occasional comments on Hidatsa social life and customs. The recording contains a minor, scratchy sound of interrmittent strength throughout, concentrated at 21:50 - 23:10, 57:05 - 01:03:26, and 01:11:55 - 01:15:09. This sound distortion has been digitally diminished as much as possible. There are also intermittent line pops from 01:02:26 - 01:10:26. The Hidatsa language is referred to on the recording by one of its alternate names, "Gros Ventre." This Gros Ventre is not to be confused with the Atsina language of the same name. This program was originally recorded on the collector's original tape 73, channel 2.
  - Conversion of Robert Hollow's Mandan Dictionary to Hidatsa: Mandan-English section, pgs. 74-93, 1971-08; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 01:20:21; Bowers, Alfred W.; Driver, James